<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-03T11:44:31+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bioimage analysis at the BICF in Copenhagen</title><subtitle>This is  a website for the Bioimaging Core Facility at the Danish Cancer Society Research Center. Here we share resources and thoughts about bioimaging and bioimage analysis.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Data Visualization for High Throughput Microscopy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dataviz,/hcs,/high-throughput/microscopy,/2020/07/02/Superplots.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Visualization for High Throughput Microscopy" /><published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dataviz,/hcs,/high-throughput/microscopy,/2020/07/02/Superplots</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dataviz,/hcs,/high-throughput/microscopy,/2020/07/02/Superplots.html">&lt;p&gt;Plotting data and statistical analysis of high-throughput microscopy (HTM) experiments is not straightforward for most microscopists and different from the way other biological experiments are usually handled. The difficulty with HTM data is that it is usually a combination of single cell data, image-level data, well/treatment-level data and plate/experiment-level data. To get accurate data on the effect of your treatment you take many images of many cells and analyze these images on a per-cell basis. We would like to do our statistical reproducibility tests on this level as well because larger &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; reduces p-values, right? But the correct way to test the effect statistically is not to treat each &lt;em&gt;cell&lt;/em&gt; but rather to treat each &lt;em&gt;treatment&lt;/em&gt; independently. After all we should assume that each cell in each treated well received the same concentration of the same drug. So for statistical testing we need to take the mean or median values for all the cells in a well, but this feels a bit like throwing out the baby with the bathwater. In fact, according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_limit_theorem&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Central Limit Theorem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, if you take multiple samples from a distribution, the distribution of the means of these samples tends towards a normal distribution, no matter what distribution the original samples were taken from. This means that your per-cell data might have odd distributions that are lost when you do the statistics on the mean values of multiple experiments. Another piece of information that that you might want to retain when taking the means of multiple experiments is if there is a certain trend for the measurements within one experiment compared to other experiments. For example if all values for one experiments are slightly higher than for the same treatments in another experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take into account both cell-level data and experiment-level data, this paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://rupress.org/jcb/article/219/6/e202001064/151717/SuperPlots-Communicating-reproducibility-and&quot;&gt;Superplots: Communicating reproducibility and variability in cell biology&lt;/a&gt; by Lord et al. published in the Journal of Cell Biology in April 2020 introduces the &lt;em&gt;Superplot&lt;/em&gt; for accurately plotting both cell-level variability and experimental reproducibility. This is from Fig 1S, an example of a Superplot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jcb_202001064_figs1_crop.png&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the average values for three experiments, in this case they trend in the same direction (what they call &lt;em&gt;“day-to-day variability”&lt;/em&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the mean of the averages plus standard error and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the distribution of the underlying per-cell data in the violinplot in the background.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is an excellent resource for every microscopist doing HTM and I think that &lt;em&gt;Superplots&lt;/em&gt; should be the go-to data visualization method for HTM experiments. A great thing about this paper is also the list of instructions they give for creating &lt;em&gt;Superplots&lt;/em&gt; with different programming languages or softwares, like Python or Graphpad Prism. After reading this paper I created the following figure in Python from one of our HTM drug screens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/avg_box_no_border_edit.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mean values for 15 independent drug treatments with 9 drugs are shown in boxplots and the underlying distribution of the per-cell data is shown in the violinplots in the background with a values for individual cells in the grey circles (I only show 15 cells per treatment). Different grey values represent different experiments. Note the skewered per-cell distributions for the yellow and light-blue treatments which wouldn’t be seen if we only show the data on the per-treatment level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="superplots" /><summary type="html">Plotting data and statistical analysis of high-throughput microscopy (HTM) experiments is not straightforward for most microscopists and different from the way other biological experiments are usually handled. The difficulty with HTM data is that it is usually a combination of single cell data, image-level data, well/treatment-level data and plate/experiment-level data. To get accurate data on the effect of your treatment you take many images of many cells and analyze these images on a per-cell basis. We would like to do our statistical reproducibility tests on this level as well because larger n reduces p-values, right? But the correct way to test the effect statistically is not to treat each cell but rather to treat each treatment independently. After all we should assume that each cell in each treated well received the same concentration of the same drug. So for statistical testing we need to take the mean or median values for all the cells in a well, but this feels a bit like throwing out the baby with the bathwater. In fact, according to the Central Limit Theorem, if you take multiple samples from a distribution, the distribution of the means of these samples tends towards a normal distribution, no matter what distribution the original samples were taken from. This means that your per-cell data might have odd distributions that are lost when you do the statistics on the mean values of multiple experiments. Another piece of information that that you might want to retain when taking the means of multiple experiments is if there is a certain trend for the measurements within one experiment compared to other experiments. For example if all values for one experiments are slightly higher than for the same treatments in another experiment. To take into account both cell-level data and experiment-level data, this paper Superplots: Communicating reproducibility and variability in cell biology by Lord et al. published in the Journal of Cell Biology in April 2020 introduces the Superplot for accurately plotting both cell-level variability and experimental reproducibility. This is from Fig 1S, an example of a Superplot: You can see: the average values for three experiments, in this case they trend in the same direction (what they call “day-to-day variability”), the mean of the averages plus standard error and the distribution of the underlying per-cell data in the violinplot in the background. This paper is an excellent resource for every microscopist doing HTM and I think that Superplots should be the go-to data visualization method for HTM experiments. A great thing about this paper is also the list of instructions they give for creating Superplots with different programming languages or softwares, like Python or Graphpad Prism. After reading this paper I created the following figure in Python from one of our HTM drug screens: The mean values for 15 independent drug treatments with 9 drugs are shown in boxplots and the underlying distribution of the per-cell data is shown in the violinplots in the background with a values for individual cells in the grey circles (I only show 15 cells per treatment). Different grey values represent different experiments. Note the skewered per-cell distributions for the yellow and light-blue treatments which wouldn’t be seen if we only show the data on the per-treatment level.</summary></entry></feed>